this time, as before, make use of the fallen stones.
This time the stones had vanished, too.
The force of the explosion had flung them to distances of hundreds of yards.
It was as though the windmill had never been.
As they approached the farm, Squealer, who had unaccountably been absent during
the fighting, came skipping towards them, whisking his tail, and beaming with satisfaction.
And the animals heard, from the direction of the farm buildings, the solemn booming of a gun.
"What is that gun firing for?"
said Boxer.
"To celebrate our victory!"
cried Squealer.
"What victory?"
said Boxer.
His knees were bleeding. He had lost a shoe and split his hoof, and a dozen
pellets had lodged themselves in his hind leg.
"What victory, comrade? Have we not driven the enemy off our soil, the
sacred soil of Animal Farm?"
"But they have destroyed the windmill.
And we had worked on it for two years."
"What matter? We will build another windmill. We will build six windmills if
we feel like it. You do not appreciate, comrade, the mighty thing that we have
done. The enemy was in occupation of this very ground that we stand upon, and
now, thanks to the leadership of Comrade Napoleon, we have won every inch of it back again.
>> Then we have won back what we had before.
>> That is our victory.
>> They limped into the yard.
The pellets under the skin of Boxer's leg smarted painfully.
He saw ahead of him the heavy labor of rebuilding the windmill from the foundations.
And already, in imagination, he braced himself for the task.
But for the first time, it occurred to him that he was 11 years old,
and that perhaps his great muscles were not quite what they had once been.
But when the animals saw the green flag flying, and heard the gun firing again,
seven times it was fired in all, and heard the speech that Napoleon made
congratulating them on their conduct, it did seem to them, after all, that they
had won a great victory.
The animals slain in the battle were given a solemn funeral.
Boxer and Clover pulled the wagon which served as a hearse, and Napoleon himself
walked at the head of the procession.
Two whole days were given over to celebrations.
There were songs, speeches, and more firing of the gun, and a special gift of
an apple was bestowed on every animal, with 2 oz of corn for each bird, and
three biscuits for each dog.
It was announced that the battle would be called the Battle of the Windmill,
and that Napoleon had created a new